<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>StatsNotebook - Simple. Powerful. Reproducible.</title>
    <link>https://statsnotebook.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on StatsNotebook - Simple. Powerful. Reproducible.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://statsnotebook.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/projects/analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/projects/analysis/</guid>
      <description>You can generate R codes for most common analyses using StatsNotebook in 30 seconds!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Visualisation</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/projects/dataviz/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 14 Sep 2020 21:13:40 +1000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/projects/dataviz/</guid>
      <description>With StatsNotebook, you can produce elegant visualisation with just a few clicks.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Data Management</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/projects/data_management/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 01 Jan 0001 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/projects/data_management/</guid>
      <description>Common data management tasks can be done with just a few clicks in StatsNotebook.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Robust regression</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/robust_regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/robust_regression/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Outliers and violations of distributional assumptions are common in many area of research. These issues might introduce substantial bias in the analysis and potentially lead to grossly incorrect inferences. Traditionally, outliers are identified through manual inspection of the data; violations of normality are often addressed by data transformation. Other forms of assumption violations, such as heterogeneity in variance, can be more challenging to address (Assumptions for linear regression can be checked using residual plots).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inverse probability treatment weighting</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/marginal_structural_model_iptw/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/marginal_structural_model_iptw/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
A time varying confounder is a variable that is affected by previous exposure, and also confounds the relationship between future exposure and outcome. Time varying confounding is common in longitudinal research. When evaluating the relationship between a time-varying exposure and outcome, standard methods such as regression and generalised linear model produce bias estimates in the presence of time-varying confounders.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IPTW with missing data</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/marginal_structural_model_iptw_with_missing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/marginal_structural_model_iptw_with_missing/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
This is a follow-up tutorial built on our tutorial on inverse probability treatment weight. In this tutorial, we use the same example, but with some missing data in the dataset. It is recommended that you read our tutorial on inverse probability treatment weight first.
The example data can be downloaded from here.
If your dataset has missing data, multiple imputation can be firstly used to impute the missing value.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IPTW/MSM</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/consultation/iptw_msm/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 04 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/consultation/iptw_msm/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
About this workshop Adjusting for time-varying confounders using IPTW for causal inference Randomized controlled trial is the gold standard for causal inference yet it is not always feasible. Multi-wave longitudinal data is increasingly used for causal inference. Standard methods such as regression yield biased results in the presence of time-varying confounders. In this workshop, I will demonstrate using Inverse probability treatment weight (IPTW) and marginal structural model (MSM) to adjust for time-varying confounders.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Line chart</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/dataviz/line_graph/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/dataviz/line_graph/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Line chart can be used to show the evoluation of numeric variables. StatsNotebook uses geom_line() from ggplot2 to build line chart.
We use the built-in Human Development Index dataset in this example. This dataset can be loaded into StatsNotebook using instruction here. This is a data from the United Nations Development Programmes (UNDP).
We will use line chart to visualise the evolution of Human Development Index from 1990 to 2018 across six regions.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Reshaping data</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/data_management/reshape/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 27 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/data_management/reshape/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
This tutorial will provide step-by-step guide on reshaping the data from
 Wide to Long Long to Wide  Wide to Long We will use the built-in Human Development Index dataset in this example. This dataset can be loaded into StatsNotebook using instruction here. This is a data from the United Nations Development Programmes (UNDP).
This dataset contains the following variables</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Scatterplot</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/dataviz/scatterplot/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 23 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/dataviz/scatterplot/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Scatterplot can be used to visualise the association between two numeric variables. StatsNotebook uses the geom_jitter function from the ggplot2 library to build scatterplot.
We use the built-in UNDP dataset in this example. This dataset can be loaded into StatsNotebook using instruction here. This is a dataset of 199 countries compiled from the United Nations Development Programme.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Barchart</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/dataviz/barchart/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/dataviz/barchart/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Bar chart can be used to visualise the frequency or proportion of categorical variables. StatsNotebook uses the geom_bar() from ggplot2 to build bar chart.
We use the built-in alcohol dataset in this example. This dataset can be loaded into StatsNotebook using instruction here. This is a simulated data of alcohol consumption from 3666 individuals.
We will use the following three variables from this dataset</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Histogram</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/dataviz/histogram/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 22 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/dataviz/histogram/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Histogram can be used to show the distribution of numeric variable. StatsNotebook uses geom_histogram() from ggplot2 to build density plot.
We use the built-in alcohol dataset in this example. This dataset can be loaded into StatsNotebook using instruction here. This is a simulated data of alcohol consumption from 3666 individuals.
We will use the following three variables from this dataset</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Density plot</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/dataviz/density/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 21 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/dataviz/density/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Density plot can be used to show the distribution of numeric variables. StatsNotebook uses geom_density() from ggplot2 to build density plot.
We use the built-in alcohol dataset in this example. This dataset can be loaded into StatsNotebook using instruction here. This is a simulated data of alcohol consumption from 3666 individuals.
We will use the following three variables from this dataset</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linear mixed model (Multilevel model)</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/linear_mixed_model/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/linear_mixed_model/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Data with multilevel (hierarchical) structure are common in many area of research. In our tutorial on moderation analysis, we examine the impact of increasing alcohol tax in Queensland on alcohol consumption. We compared changes in alcohol consumption for individuals from Queensland before and after the implementation of tax increase, compared to changes in alcohol consumption in other states.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Compute variables</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/data_management/compute_variable/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/data_management/compute_variable/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
StatsNotebook provides a simple menu for creating new variables. We will give two examples below to demonstrate using StatsNotebook to compute new variables.
 Log transformation Creating a quadratic term  In these two examples, we will use the built-in Personality dataset. This dataset can be loaded into StatsNotebook using instruction here or can be downloaded from here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Residual plots and assumption checking</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/linearity_homoscedasticity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/linearity_homoscedasticity/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
A residual plot is an essential tool for checking the assumption of linearity and homoscedasticity. The following are examples of residual plots when (1) the assumptions are met, (2) the homoscedasticity assumption is violated and (3) the linearity assumption is violated.
Assumption met When both the assumption of linearity and homoscedasticity are met, the points in the residual plot (plotting standardised residuals against predicted values) will be randomly scattered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Causal Mediation Analysis</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/mediation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/mediation/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Mediation analysis is a technique that examines the intermediate process by which the independent variable affects the dependent variable. For example, family intervention during adolescence (independent variable) can reduce engagement with deviant peer group (mediator) and their experimentation with drugs, which in turn reduces risk of substance use disorder in young adulthood (dependent variable).
StatsNotebook uses the cutting-edge counterfactual framework and Monte Carlo technique to conduct causal mediation analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Imputation</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/multiple_imputation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/multiple_imputation/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Missing data is a norm rather than an exception in most areas of research. Excluding observations with missing data reduces statistical power and potentially introduces bias in model estimates. Multiple imputation is a technique that fills in missing values based on the available data. It can increase statistical power and reduce the bias due to missing data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moderation (Interaction) analysis using linear regression</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/moderation_interaction_regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/moderation_interaction_regression/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Assumed knowledge in this tutorial: Linear regression
Moderation analysis is used to examine if the effect of an independent variable on the dependent variable is the same across different levels of another independent variable (moderator). In other words, it is used to examine whether the moderator will change the strength of the relationship between the independent and dependent variables.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Boxplot</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/dataviz/boxplot/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/dataviz/boxplot/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Boxplot is commonly used to compare distribution of a numeric variables across several groups. StatsNotebook uses geom_boxplot() from ggplot2 to build boxplot.
We use the built-in alcohol dataset in this example. This dataset can be loaded into StatsNotebook using instruction here. This is a simulated data of alcohol consumption from 3666 individuals.
We will use the following three variables from this dataset</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Correlogram</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/dataviz/correlogram/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/dataviz/correlogram/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Correlogram is a type of chart that visualise the pairwise association between variables. StatsNotebook uses the ggpairs() function from the GGally library to build correlogram. A publication ready correlogram can be built within a few minutes with StatsNotebook.
We use the built-in Personality dataset in this example. This dataset can be loaded into StatsNotebook using instruction here or can be downloaded from here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Descriptive statistics</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/descriptive/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/descriptive/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
This tutorial will give a short introduction on descriptive analysis using StatsNotebook. Descriptive statistics such as mean, standard deviation, median and interquartile range can be easily obtained using the Explore panel.
We use the built-in Personality dataset in this example. This dataset can be loaded into StatsNotebook using the instructions provided here or can be downloaded from here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Load Example Data</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/data_management/load_example_data/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/data_management/load_example_data/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
StatsNotebook comes with a rich data library for learning statistics. To load an example dataset,
 Click the Menu icon  at the top Click &amp;ldquo;Open&amp;rdquo; Select &amp;ldquo;Example Data&amp;rdquo; from the menu  Click on the example data we want to load.  Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Set reference for categorical variables</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/data_management/set_reference/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/data_management/set_reference/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
For categorical variable, it is important to set a &amp;ldquo;reference&amp;rdquo; category in many analyses. For example, for the variable Sex in our regression analysis tutorial, the default reference is Female. The coefficient of SexMale from the regression represents the effect of male relative to female. In this case, the coefficient -0.87 means that the depression score (the dependent variable in that analysis) for male is 0.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Variable types in R and StatsNotebook</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/data_management/variable_conversion/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/data_management/variable_conversion/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
There are four major variable types in StatsNotebook: Categorical, Numeric, Date and Character. By default, when data is loaded into StatsNotebook, the variables are either Numeric or Character variables.
Categorical variables Categorical variables are variables that have two or more categories. For example, sex is a categorical variable that we can code into male and female. Another exapmle is color, which we can code into Yellow, Red, Orange, etc.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Violin plot</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/dataviz/violinplot/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/dataviz/violinplot/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Violin plot can be used to visualise the distribution of a numeric variable across several groups. StatsNotebook uses geom_violin() from ggplot2 to build violin plot.
We use the built-in alcohol dataset in this example. This dataset can be loaded into StatsNotebook using instruction here. This is a simulated data of alcohol consumption from 3666 individuals.
We will use the following three variables from this dataset</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Beta version now available</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/betarelease/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/betarelease/</guid>
      <description>StatsNotebook 0.1.0 is now available for Windows in the download page. Try out the next generation of statistical software now!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linear Regression</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/regression/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Linear regression is a technique for examining the relationship between a dependent variable (outcome) and a set of independent variables (predictors). This tutorial demonstrates how to conduct a linear regression in StatsNotebook using the following example. We will also provide an example write-up in APA style.
Example research questions  Are the Big 5 personality traits, Agreeableness, Conscientiousness, Extraversion, Neuroticism, and Openness, associated with depression?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linear regression with missing data</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/regression_missingdata/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/regression_missingdata/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
In many area of research, missing data is a norm rather than an exception. Dropping observations/ participants with missing data is usually not appropriate as it reduces statistical power and also may introduce bias in analysis. This tutorial will demonstrate a simple way in StatsNotebook to handle missing data using multiple imputation.
In our linear regression tutorial, we use the personality dataset to examine two research qeustions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>