<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Analysis on StatsNotebook - Simple. Powerful. Reproducible.</title>
    <link>https://gckc123.github.io/tags/analysis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Analysis on StatsNotebook - Simple. Powerful. Reproducible.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://gckc123.github.io/tags/analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Robust regression</title>
      <link>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/robust_regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 24 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/robust_regression/</guid>
      <description>Outliers and violation of distributional assumptions are common in many area of research. These issues might introduce substantial bias in the analysis and potentially lead to grossly incorrect inference. Traditionally, outliers are identified through manual inspection of the data; violation of normality are often addressed by data transformation. Other forms of assumption violation, such as heterogeneity in variance, can be more challenging to address. Robust regression is a technique that can reduce the impact of outliers and other forms of assumption violations.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis</title>
      <link>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/</guid>
      <description>All analyses in StatsNotebook are conducted in R.
 Descriptive statistics Linear regression (with missing data) Moderation/ Interaction Analysis Causal mediation analysis Multiple imputation for missing data Robust regression  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Causal Mediation Analysis</title>
      <link>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/mediation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/mediation/</guid>
      <description>Mediation analysis is a technique that examines the intermediate process by which the indepedent variable affects the dependent variable. For example, family intervention during adolescence (independent variable) can reduce engagement with deviant peer group (mediator) and their experimentation with drugs, which in turn reduce risk of substance use disorder in young adulthood (dependent variable).
StatsNotebook uses the cutting edge counterfactual framework and Monte Carlo technique to conduct causal mediation analysis. It can handle</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Imputation</title>
      <link>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/multiple_imputation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/multiple_imputation/</guid>
      <description>Missing data is a norm rather than an exception in most area of research. Excluding observations with missing data reduces statistical power and potentially introduces bias in model estimates. Multiple imputation is a technique that fills in missing value based on available data. It can increase statistical power and reduce bias due to missing data.
StatsNotebook provides a simple interface for multiple imputation using the mice package. By default, numeric variables are imputed using predictive mean matching and categorical variables are imputed using multinomial logistic regression (for categorical variables with 3 or more level) or binary logistic regression (for categorical variables with 2 levels).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moderation (Interaction) analysis using linear regression</title>
      <link>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/moderation_interaction_regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/moderation_interaction_regression/</guid>
      <description>Assumed knowledge in this tutorial: Linear regression
Moderation analysis is used to examine if the effect of an independent variable on the dependent variable is the same across different level of another independent variable (moderator). In an other word, it is for examining if the moderator change the strength of the relationship between the independent and dependent variables.
Example research questions Is the effect of psychotherapy (independent variable) on depression (dependent variable) stronger for female than for male (moderator: sex)?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Descriptive statistics</title>
      <link>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/descriptive/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/descriptive/</guid>
      <description>This tutorial will give a short introduction on descriptive analysis using StatsNotebook. Descriptive statistcs such as mean, standard deviation, median and interquartile range can be easily obtained using the Explore panel.
We use the built-in Personality dataset in this example. This dataset can be loaded into StatsNotebook using instruction here or can be downloaded from here.
The Personality dataset contains data from 231 participants, with measures on the Big 5 personality factors (Agreeableness, Conscientiousness, Extraversion, neuroticism and Openness), three measures of mental health (Depression, Trait anxiety and State anxiety).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Descriptive statistics</title>
      <link>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/data_management/compute_variable/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/data_management/compute_variable/</guid>
      <description>Coming soon&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linear mixed model (Multilevel linear model)</title>
      <link>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/linear_mixed_model/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/linear_mixed_model/</guid>
      <description>Coming soon&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Violation of linearity and homoscedasticity</title>
      <link>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/linearity_homoscedasticity/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/linearity_homoscedasticity/</guid>
      <description>Coming soon&amp;hellip;</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linear Regression</title>
      <link>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/regression/</guid>
      <description>Linear regression is a technique for examining the relationship between a dependent variable (outcome) and a set of independent variables (predictors). This tutorial demonstrates how to conduct a linear regression in StatsNotebook using the following example. We will also provide an example write-up in APA styles.
Example research questions Are the Big 5 personality traits, Agreeableness, Conscientiousness, Extraversion, Neuroticism, and Openness, associated with depression? Is sex associated with depression?  In this setup, the dependent variable is depression, the independent variables are Agreeableness, Conscientiousness, Extraversion, Neuroticism, Openness and sex.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linear regression with missing data</title>
      <link>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/regression_missingdata/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://gckc123.github.io/blog/analysis/regression_missingdata/</guid>
      <description>In many area of research, missing data is a norm rather than an exception. Dropping observations/ participants with missing data is usually not appropriate as it reduces statistical power and also may introduce bias in analysis. This tutorial will demonstrate a simple way in StatsNotebook to handle missing data using multiple imputation.
In our linear regression tutorial, we use the personality dataset to examine two research qeustions.
 Are the Big 5 personality traits, Agreeableness, Conscientiousness, Extraversion, Neuroticism, and Openness, associated with depression?</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>