<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Analysis on StatsNotebook - Simple. Powerful. Reproducible.</title>
    <link>https://statsnotebook.io/tags/analysis/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Analysis on StatsNotebook - Simple. Powerful. Reproducible.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://statsnotebook.io/tags/analysis/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Robust regression</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/robust_regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 08 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/robust_regression/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Outliers and violations of distributional assumptions are common in many area of research. These issues might introduce substantial bias in the analysis and potentially lead to grossly incorrect inferences. Traditionally, outliers are identified through manual inspection of the data; violations of normality are often addressed by data transformation. Other forms of assumption violations, such as heterogeneity in variance, can be more challenging to address (Assumptions for linear regression can be checked using residual plots).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Inverse probability treatment weighting</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/marginal_structural_model_iptw/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/marginal_structural_model_iptw/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
A time varying confounder is a variable that is affected by previous exposure, and also confounds the relationship between future exposure and outcome. Time varying confounding is common in longitudinal research. When evaluating the relationship between a time-varying exposure and outcome, standard methods such as regression and generalised linear model produce bias estimates in the presence of time-varying confounders.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>IPTW with missing data</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/marginal_structural_model_iptw_with_missing/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 05 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/marginal_structural_model_iptw_with_missing/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
This is a follow-up tutorial built on our tutorial on inverse probability treatment weight. In this tutorial, we use the same example, but with some missing data in the dataset. It is recommended that you read our tutorial on inverse probability treatment weight first.
The example data can be downloaded from here.
If your dataset has missing data, multiple imputation can be firstly used to impute the missing value.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linear mixed model (Multilevel model)</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/linear_mixed_model/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 20 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/linear_mixed_model/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Data with multilevel (hierarchical) structure are common in many area of research. In our tutorial on moderation analysis, we examine the impact of increasing alcohol tax in Queensland on alcohol consumption. We compared changes in alcohol consumption for individuals from Queensland before and after the implementation of tax increase, compared to changes in alcohol consumption in other states.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Residual plots and assumption checking</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/linearity_homoscedasticity/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 16 Oct 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/linearity_homoscedasticity/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
A residual plot is an essential tool for checking the assumption of linearity and homoscedasticity. The following are examples of residual plots when (1) the assumptions are met, (2) the homoscedasticity assumption is violated and (3) the linearity assumption is violated.
Assumption met When both the assumption of linearity and homoscedasticity are met, the points in the residual plot (plotting standardised residuals against predicted values) will be randomly scattered.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Analysis</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
All analyses in StatsNotebook are conducted in R.
 Descriptive statistics Linear regression (with missing data) Moderation/ Interaction Analysis Causal mediation analysis Multiple imputation for missing data Robust regression Residual plots and assumption checking for linear regression Linear mixed model (Multilevel model) Inverse probability treatment weight for longitudinal study (with missing data)  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Causal Mediation Analysis</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/mediation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/mediation/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Mediation analysis is a technique that examines the intermediate process by which the independent variable affects the dependent variable. For example, family intervention during adolescence (independent variable) can reduce engagement with deviant peer group (mediator) and their experimentation with drugs, which in turn reduces risk of substance use disorder in young adulthood (dependent variable).
StatsNotebook uses the cutting-edge counterfactual framework and Monte Carlo technique to conduct causal mediation analysis.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Imputation</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/multiple_imputation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/multiple_imputation/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Missing data is a norm rather than an exception in most areas of research. Excluding observations with missing data reduces statistical power and potentially introduces bias in model estimates. Multiple imputation is a technique that fills in missing values based on the available data. It can increase statistical power and reduce the bias due to missing data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Moderation (Interaction) analysis using linear regression</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/moderation_interaction_regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/moderation_interaction_regression/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Assumed knowledge in this tutorial: Linear regression
Moderation analysis is used to examine if the effect of an independent variable on the dependent variable is the same across different levels of another independent variable (moderator). In other words, it is used to examine whether the moderator will change the strength of the relationship between the independent and dependent variables.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Descriptive statistics</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/descriptive/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 20 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/descriptive/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
This tutorial will give a short introduction on descriptive analysis using StatsNotebook. Descriptive statistics such as mean, standard deviation, median and interquartile range can be easily obtained using the Explore panel.
We use the built-in Personality dataset in this example. This dataset can be loaded into StatsNotebook using the instructions provided here or can be downloaded from here.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linear Regression</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/regression/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/regression/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Linear regression is a technique for examining the relationship between a dependent variable (outcome) and a set of independent variables (predictors). This tutorial demonstrates how to conduct a linear regression in StatsNotebook using the following example. We will also provide an example write-up in APA style.
Example research questions  Are the Big 5 personality traits, Agreeableness, Conscientiousness, Extraversion, Neuroticism, and Openness, associated with depression?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linear regression with missing data</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/regression_missingdata/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/regression_missingdata/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
In many area of research, missing data is a norm rather than an exception. Dropping observations/ participants with missing data is usually not appropriate as it reduces statistical power and also may introduce bias in analysis. This tutorial will demonstrate a simple way in StatsNotebook to handle missing data using multiple imputation.
In our linear regression tutorial, we use the personality dataset to examine two research qeustions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>