<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Missing data on StatsNotebook - Simple. Powerful. Reproducible.</title>
    <link>https://statsnotebook.io/tags/missing-data/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Missing data on StatsNotebook - Simple. Powerful. Reproducible.</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="https://statsnotebook.io/tags/missing-data/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>Multiple Imputation</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/multiple_imputation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/multiple_imputation/</guid>
      <description>Follow us on Facebook or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
Missing data is a norm rather than an exception in most areas of research. Excluding observations with missing data reduces statistical power and potentially introduces bias in model estimates. Multiple imputation is a technique that fills in missing values based on the available data. It can increase statistical power and reduce the bias due to missing data.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Linear regression with missing data</title>
      <link>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/regression_missingdata/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://statsnotebook.io/blog/analysis/regression_missingdata/</guid>
      <description>Follow our Facebook page or our developer&amp;rsquo;s Twitter for more tutorials and future updates
In many area of research, missing data is a norm rather than an exception. Dropping observations/ participants with missing data is usually not appropriate as it reduces statistical power and also may introduce bias in analysis. This tutorial will demonstrate a simple way in StatsNotebook to handle missing data using multiple imputation.
In our linear regression tutorial, we use the personality dataset to examine two research qeustions.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>